Finding Aid for Joseph Ralston Hayden Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- File maintained by Lloyd Millegan
  - JRH's mission to China and Australia for the Office of Strategic Services, papers about (Box 41)
    (41-5)
  - Conditions in the Sulu Archipelago and war intelligence objectives in the Sulu, papers about (Box 41)
    (41-6)
  - Memorandum of conferences with MacArthur, Willoughby, and Merle-Smith regarding O.S.S. operations in the Southwest Pacific Area (Box 41)
    (41-7)
  - China and JRH's activities in Chungking, China in 1942 papers about, 1940-1944 (Box 41)
    (41-8)
  - Military espionage and spies, bibliography relating to, undated (Box 41)
    (41-9)
  - Co-ordinator of Information and the Office of Strategic Services, papers about, 1941-1942 (Box 41)
    (41-10)
  - Korean Provisional Government and the Korean Army (Box 41)
    (41-11)
  - Trip to China, reports and notes concerning, 1942-1943 (Box 41)
    (41-12)
  - Philippines, clippings and miscellanea about, 1932-1944 (Box 41)
    (41-13)
  - Esson M. Gale, correspondence with, 1942 (Box 41)
    (41-14)
  - James R. Fugate, papers about, 1936-1939 (Box 41)
    (41-15)
  - Memo from JRH relating to a memorandum to Colonel Donovan from Pearl Buck discussing the role of China in the war effort, 1942 (Box 41)
    (41-16)
  - Statement of Edward M. Kuder written to JRH on events and conditions in Lanao immediately preceding the war and from, 1941-1943; 1943 (Box 41)
    (includes appendices on the problems of government in predominately Moslem provinces)
    (41-17)
  - Maps-road map of the Philippines 1940 and map of the Coral Sea Strategic Area, 1942, 1940-1942 (Box 41)
    (41-18)
  - Memoranda from Colonel R.A. Dunn on the Philippine situation, January-February 1942 (Box 41)
    (41-19)
  - Papers from General Frank Parker to Senator Millard Tydings concerning proposed naval site in the Philippine Islands; also related map, 1934; undated (Box 41)
    (41-20)
  - Question of legal authority for U.S. intervention in the Philippines, letter to J. Weldon Jones about, 1942 (Box 41)
    (41-21)
  - War effort in the Philippines, miscellanea about, 1942-1944 (Box 41)
    (41-22)
  - Revised Administrative Code of, 1917 (Box 41)
    (41-23)
  - Preliminary report entitled "Philippine Civil Affairs: Policy and Organization", April 16, 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-1)
  - Notes of conversations with General Douglas MacArthur, 1944-1945 (Box 42)
    (42-2)
  - Notes of conversations with Manuel Quezon, including drafts of statement on conferences, March 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-3)
  - Miscellaneous notes and directives from Manuel Quezon, 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-4)
  - Question of presidential succession in the Philippines, copies of correspondence between Quezon, Osmena, and Roosevelt, 1943 (Box 42)
    (42-5)
  - Evolution of a civil affairs policy for the Philippines, papers concerning, 1943-1944 (Box 42)
    (42-6)
  - Philippine collaboration, papers concerning, 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-7)
  - Treatment of American POW's and civilian internees in the Philippines, papers concerning, 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-8)
  - Status and duties of the Commonwealth Government, the Commander-in-Chief, and the High Commissioner upon reoccupation, papers concerning (Box 42)
    (42-9)
  - Report: "Principles governing arrangements for civil administration and jurisdiction in Netherlands Territory in the southwest Pacific area" (Box 42)
    (42-10)
  - Telegrams of condolence upon the death of Manuel Quezon, August 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-11)
  - Continuance of Quezon as Commonwealth President after November 1943 papers concerning, 1943 (Box 42)
    (42-12)
  - Constitutional status of the Philippines during the war, paper written by UM Law School dean Henry M. Bates, papers about, 1943 (Box 42)
    (42-13)
  - Provincial government of Palawan, report concerning, 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-14)
  - Report of the Philippine Research and Information Section, April 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-15)
  - Report entitled "Who's Who in the Philippines", September 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-16)
  - Bibliography of Philippine materials in the Library of the Files and Studies Section, G-5, October 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-17)
  - "Philippine Biographies,", October 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-18)
  - Directory of Philippine Commonwealth Officials, April 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-19)
  - Report entitled "Conditions Affecting Domestic Order in the Moro Provinces of Mindanao and Sulu", August 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-20)
  - "The Philippines during the Japanese Regime and annotated list of the literature published in or about the Philippines during the Japanese Occupation", 1942-1945 (Box 42)
    (42-21)
  - Guest log of the Philippine Research and Information Section, December 1944-April 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-22)
  - Philippine Research and Information Section, miscellaneous papers about (Box 42)
    (42-23)
  - Report by Hernando Abaya entitled "Collaboration & Collaborators, Philippine Version", May 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-24)
  - Report entitled "Law Enforcement in the Philippine Islands", September 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-25)
  - Report presenting a plan for the establishment of a constabulary force in Moro areas upon reoccupation, October 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-26)
  - Plan presented by Lloyd Millegan for the cultural reorganization of the Philippines, April 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-27)
  - Plan for psychological warfare in the southwest Pacific area, July 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-28)
  - Reports of conferences between Jose Laurel and the Japanese, 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-29)
  - Report of Chick Parsons to Manuel Quezon concerning the Philippine situation; and Quezon's reply, September 1943 (Box 42)
    (42-30)
  - Memo concerning evacuees from the Philippines, September 1943-August 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-321)
  - Papers concerning civilian internees in Santo Tomas prison camp, 1943 (Box 42)
    (42-32)
  - Report entitled "Local Problems: Pangasinan Province, 26 April 1945" (Box 42)
    (42-33)
  - Report entitled "The Hukbalahap", March 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-34)
  - Report concerning Makapili and Ganaps in Nueva Ecija, February 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-35)
  - History of USAFIP, North Luzon and guerrilla activities in North Luzon, February 1945 (Box 42)
    (42-36)
  - Reports from Dionisio Gutierrez, including material on guerrilla activities in Mindanao, 1944-1945 (Box 42)
    (42-37)
  - Correspondence of Lt. Commander F.L. Worcester concerning the guerrilla situation in Mindanao, 1943-1944 (Box 42)
    (42-38)
  - Draft of speech entitled "The Philippines will not be conquered" (Box 42)
    (42-39)
  - Paper entitled "The Philippine Public Schools: A brief appraisal" (Box 42)
    (42-41)
  - Death of Manuel Quezon, papers concerning, 1944-1945 (Box 42)
    (42-42)
  - Death of Sergio Osmena, papers concerning, 1944 (Box 42)
    (42-43)
  - Miscellaneous personal papers, 1944-1945 (Box 42)
    (42-44; 42-45)
  - Malolos Constitution, 1899 (Box 42)
    (original copy)
    (42-46)
  - Documents prepared by the Institute of Pacific Relations, including "The Philippine Policy of the United States" by JRH, 1939 (Box 42)
    (42-47)
- Files maintained by Elizabeth Olivia Hayden
  (1985 accession to the collection)
  The series titled Files maintained by Elizabeth Olivia Hayden was donated in 1985-86 following the death of Mrs. J.R. Hayden. This series consists of Hayden's personal correspondence with his wife and family members, personal subject files mainly from the period of World War II, and papers of Elizabeth Olivia Hayden's family, Hall family. This latter portion of the collection is unprocessed.
  - Correspondence
    - circa 1908-1975, 5 folders (Box 43)
    - 1908-1921, 23 folders (Box 43)
    - 1922-1940, 24 folders (Box 44)
    - 1941-April 1945, 16 folders (Box 45)
    - July 1945-1958, 18 folders (Box 46)
    - 1959-1975, 17 folders (Box 47)
  - Death of Joseph Ralston Hayden
    - Correspondence with Elizabeth O. Hall Hayden, May-November 1945; 4 folders (Box 47)
      (largely letters of condolence)
    - Miscellaneous documents pertaining to the death of Joseph R. Hayden (Box 47)
    - Condolence cards (Box 47)
  - Elizabeth O. Hall Hayden diaries
    - Trip to Mindanao, 1931 (Box 47)
      (original and typescript)
    - Daily diaries, 1934-1935; 3 folders (Box 47)
      (originals and partial typescript copies)
  - Subject files
    - Brent School, Baguio (Box 48)
    - Engagement books/calendars (Box 48)
    - Handwritten notes, 1908-1946 (Box 48)
    - Hayden, Elizabeth Douglas (personal) (Box 48)
    - Hayden, Joseph Ralston (personal)
      - Cunningham, Bill (Box 48)
      - Manila Polo Club (Box 48)
      - Rotary Club (Box 48)
      - Stock account (Box 48)
    - Miscellaneous Philippine material (Box 48)
    - Miscellaneous material pertaining to travel abroad and in the United States, 2 folders (Box 48)
    - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1908-1946 (Box 48)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 48)
    - Philippine Diary (kept by JRH), 1933-1935 (Box 48)
    - "Powers of the President of the Philippines" (Box 48)
    - Visual material (Box 48)
  - JRH Philippine subject files, 1933-1934
    - Army-Navy Club, 1933-1934 (Box 48)
    - Kalaw, Maximo M (dean, University of the Philippines) (Box 48)
    - Ogg, F.A (Box 48)
    - Oratorical Association (Box 48)
    - Philippine Bibliography (Box 48)
    - Smith, Shirley W (Box 48)
    - Student Conference on World Affairs (Box 48)
    - University Council (Box 48)
    - University of Michigan
      - General (Box 48)
      - Extension (Box 48)
  - JRH personal/subject file
    - Master file (personal), September 17, 1941-December 31, 1941 (Box 49)
    - Master file (personal), January 2-September 21 (Box 49)
    - A (Box 49)
    - A.N. Marquis Company (Box 49)
    - Address material (Box 49)
    - American Council of Learned Societies (Box 49)
    - American Geographical Society of New York (Box 49)
    - Ann Arbor Committee for National Defense (Box 49)
    - Ann Arbor Trust Company (Box 49)
    - Archives (National Archives) (Box 49)
    - Automobile (Box 49)
    - B (Box 49)
    - Bishop Brent Moro School (Box 49)
    - Boerner, Alfred V (Box 49)
    - Boyd, William M (Box 49)
    - Callis, H.G (Box 49)
    - Cash, Harry L (Box 49)
    - Clippings (Box 49)
    - Colegrove, Kenneth: "East Asia, the New Order In" (Box 49)
    - Congressional Record (Box 49)
    - D (Box 49)
    - Davis, Captain Ward P (Box 49)
    - Dorchester House (Box 49)
    - E (Box 49)
    - Earle, Edward Mead (Box 49)
    - East Indies Institute of America, Inc (Box 49)
    - East, protest in the-Phi Kappa Phi (Box 49)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica (Box 49)
    - Excerpts from newspapers (Box 49)
    - Expense account (Box 49)
    - Eyre, James K., Jr (Box 49)
    - F (Box 49)
    - Foreign Policy Bulletins (Box 49)
    - Foreign Relations
      - Committees of (organization and functions) (Box 49)
      - Council on Far East Study Group (Box 49)
      - Council on Foreign Relations (Dr. Percy Bidwell) (Box 49)
      - Detroit Committee on Foreign Relations (Box 49)
      - New York Council on Foreign Relations (W.H. Mallory, executive director) (Box 49)
    - Fugate, James R (Box 49)
    - G (Box 49)
    - Gage, Alexander Kimball, Jr (Box 49)
    - Gause, W.A (Box 49)
    - George Washington University (Box 49)
    - H (Box 49)
    - Hall, H. Duncan (Box 49)
    - Hawaii: Restless Rampart (by Joseph Barber Jr.) (Box 49)
    - Hawaii, University of (Box 49)
    - Hayden/Ralston family miscellaneous, 1854-1903 (scattered) (Box 49)
    - Hayden, Joseph R. (miscellaneous forms and applications) (Box 49)
    - Hayden, Mary (Box 49)
    - Hayden, Ralston: Western Reserve University (Box 49)
    - Hayden, Van Brocklin (Box 49)
    - Hobart College (Box 49)
    - Hoover Ball & Bearing Company (Box 49)
    - Horse: Hutton's King: F.W. McLane (Box 49)
    - Hu Smith, Dr. (i.e. Huh Shih) (Box 49)
    - J (Box 49)
    - Jappe, James L.E (Box 49)
    - Jones, J. Weldon (Box 49)
    - I (Box 49)
    - International Studies Conference (Box 49)
    - Iowa, State :University of (Box 49)
    - K (Box 49)
    - Knopf, Alfred A., Inc (Box 49)
    - L (Box 49)
    - Loan to China (Box 49)
    - Mc (Box 49)
    - McNutt, Paul V (Box 49)
    - M (Box 49)
    - Macmillan Company, 2 folders (Box 49)
    - Maps: Philippines, Mindanao and Sulu Peninsula (Box 49)
    - Michigan, University of
      - Bartlett, H.H (Box 49)
      - Bromage, Arthur (Box 49)
      - Brown, Everett S (Box 49)
      - Gale, Esson M (Box 49)
      - Karpinsky, Louis C (Box 49)
      - Kraus, Edward (Box 49)
      - Losh, Hazel (Box 49)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 49)
      - Perkins, John A (Box 49)
      - Watkins, Herbert G (Box 49)
      - Woodburne, Lloyd (Box 49)
    - Millegan, Lloyd S (Box 49)
    - Minnesota, University of (William Anderson) (Box 49)
    - Monmouth College (Dr. Robert W. McCulloch) (Box 49)
    - Murphy, Frank (Box 49)
    - N (Box 49)
    - National Defense and Economic Reconstruction (National Industrial Conference Board, Inc.) (Box 49)
    - National Policy Committee (Box 49)
    - New Jersey State Teacher's College(Lawrence H. Conrad) (Box 49)
    - New York, Hunter College of (Madge M. McKinney) (Box 49)
    - O (Box 49)
    - Owings, Chloe (Box 49)
    - P (Box 49)
    - Pacific Relations, American Council Institute of (Box 49)
    - Parker, Frank (Box 49)
    - Pearson, Lawrence W (Box 49)
    - Personnel data (Box 49)
    - Philippines: Far East (Box 49)
    - Philippine News (Box 49)
    - Philippine export taxes (Box 49)
    - The Philippines (Box 49)
    - Philippines (Millegan) (Box 49)
    - Philippines (Quezon) (Box 49)
    - Porter, Andrew O (Box 49)
    - Powers of the President of the Philippines (Box 49)
    - Q (Box 49)
    - R (Box 49)
    - Rivers, William C (Box 49)
    - Rochester, University of (Dr. Alan Valentine, president) (Box 49)
    - S (Box 49)
    - Salter, Mrs. John P (Box 49)
    - Sayre, Francis B. (High Commissioner to the Philippines) (Box 49)
    - Smith, Harold D.: "The Management of Government in a Democracy" (Box 49)
    - Smith, Robert Aura (Box 49)
    - Social Science Research Council (Box 49)
    - Solomon, Harriet E (Box 49)
    - Stamps and covers (Box 49)
    - Stricker, Henry D (Box 49)
    - Sulit, Estella R (Box 49)
    - T (Box 49)
    - Training School (Box 49)
    - Trans Siberian Railway (Box 49)
    - Travel authorization (Box 49)
    - W (Box 49)
    - Whitney, Courtney R (Box 49)
    - Wisconsin, University of (Box 49)
    - Young (Box 49)
    - Ephemera, 2 folders (Box 49)
- Hall family
  - Family letters and other papers (Box 50)
    (unprocessed)
  - Family letters and other papers (Box 51)
  - Family letters and other papers (Box 52)
  - Family letters and other papers (Box 53)
  - Family letters and other papers (Box 54)
  - Family letters and other papers (Box 55)
Selected Index to Correspondence
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.
1928 (Feb. 10 and 20)
Artiaga, Santiago, 1878-1962.
June 23, 1939
Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937.
August 18, 1916; 1925 (July 23 and 25)
Carpenter, Frank Watson
December 9, 1933; 1934 (Jan. 17, Feb. 26, May 9 and Dec. 1)
Clements, William Lawrence, 1861-1934.
1927 (Feb. 4, 5 and 8)
Cox, Creed Fulton, 1877-1950.
1933 (Nov. 7, 11, 13, and 15)
Crawford, Fred Lewis, 1888-1957.
Feb. 26, 1937
Diekema, Gerrit John, 1859-1930.
1929 (June 7 and 8)
Forbes, William Cameron, 1870-1959.
Dec. 21, 1921; 1927 (June 20, July 5 and 12, and Sept. 19); Dec. 31, 1929; Jan. 15, 1930; Jan. 28, 1934
Fugate, James R., d. 1938.
1921, Nov. 12, 1928, and 1930-1938 (throughout)
Gilmore, Eugene Allen, 1871-1953
1927, 1929, 1931 (Sept. 3 and Dec. 2); 1932 (Jan. 3 and 5)
Green, Fred Warren, 1872-1936.
Apr. 2, 1929; 1930 (Mar. 19, 24 and 26)
Guest, Edgar Albert, 1881-1959.
Correspondence scattered throughout
Harllee, William C.
1935 (Sept. 1 and Oct. 3); 1936 Aug. 23, Sept. 26 and Dec. 15)
Harrison, Francis Burton, 1873-1957.
Aug. 18, 1916
Hester, Everett D.
Dec. 14, 1932, 1933, 1937 (Mar. 30 and May 8); 1941 (May 23 and July 8)
Hill, Norman Hingston
1933 (July 22 and Dec. 15); 1936 (Feb. 25 and July 6); April 13, 1927
Hornbeck, Stanley Kuhl, 1883-1966.
Oct. 25, 1932, Nov. 12, 1933, Jan. 29, 1934, 1936 (Aug. 15, 19, and 24, Oct. 21)
Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.
Nov. 25, 1938
Jones, James Weldon
1935-1937; 1940-1941
Kellogg, Frank Billings, 1856-1937
June 20, 1928
Kuder, Edward M.
May 1, 1934
Laurel, Jose
Correspondence scattered throughout
McNutt, Paul Vories, 1891-1955
July 30, 1937, Oct. 4, 1938
Malcolm, George Arthur, 1881-1961.
Dec. 31, 1925, June 16, 1928, Aug. 30, 1937, March 18, 1940
Michener, Earl Cory, 1876-1957.
Mar. 3, 1926, 1929, April 1930, 1932 (May 10, October 25 and Nov. 10)
Mosher, Gouverneur Frank, 1871-1941.
Nov. 15, 1932, 1933 (July 20 & Nov. 4), Aug. 21, 1934, 1936, Apr. 28, 1937, 1939, Feb. 1, 1940
Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.
Aug. 2, 1933, 1934, 1935 (Dec. 5 and 10), 1936-1939, 1940 (Apr. 9 and May 6)
Osias, Camilo
Oct. 21, 1930, 1932 (Nov. 3 and 8)
Parker, Francis LeJau, 1873-
1933 (July 24 and 26, Aug. 19, 21 and 25)
Parker, Frank, 1872-1947.
Correspondence scattered throughout
Pollock, James Kerr, 1898-1968.
July 31, 1929, Sept. 1, 1934, Sept. 10, 1935
Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944.
1927 (Nov. 21 and 26), July 28, 1936
Ralston, Jackson Harvey, 1857-1945.
1927 (Apr. 27, May 21), 1929 (July 14 and Sept. 7), June 16, 1931, Nov. 3, 1933, 1934 (Feb. 21 and Dec. 12), 1937 (Jan. 19, Feb. 12 and June 24), 1938 (July 10 and Oct. 8), 1939, 1941 (June 8. Aug. 4 and Sept. 4)
Reeves, Jesse Siddall, 1872-1942.
1934 (Jan. 6 and June 26)
Romulo, Carlos P., 1901-
May 10, 1935
Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, 1882-1945.
Apr. 13, 1936
Roth, Fred G.
1934-1935, Aug. 29, 1936, Feb. 11, 1937, 1938 (Mar. 5 and May 6), 1939, 1940 (Feb. 6 and Mar. 28)
Roxas, Manuel
1932-1933, Aug. 21, 1934
Sayre, Francis Bowes, 1885-
1937 (May 4 and 10)
Swanson, Claude Augustus, 1862-1939.
Dec. 6, 1917, June 15, 1928
Taft, William Howard, 1857-1930.
Nov. 24, 1928
Tomlinson, Mathew
Correspondence scattered throughout
Vandenberg, Arthur Hendrick, 1884-1951.
1928 (Apr. 2 and 9), 1929-1930, 1931 (Oct. 16 and Nov. 25), 1932, Feb. 20, 1936
Van Schaick, Louis J.
Oct. 6, 1931, 1935 (Apr. 2 and July 9), Nov. 3, 1936
Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.
Aug. 15, 1922, 1924, Dec. 19, 1925, 1926 (Jan. 25 and June 3), July 1927
Worcester, Nanon Fay Leas
May 17, 1927